A.E. (Gene) Magee Photographs and Papers 1902-1996 (bulk 1930-1970)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
A.E. (Gene) Magee Photographs and Papers 1902-1996 (bulk 1930-1970)
MS 573
Magee, A.E. (Gene), 1907-1999.
This collection contains photographic prints, negatives, slides and a small number of papers created by A.E. (Gene) Magee from the 1920’s-1990’s. Subjects include aerial imagery of Tucson, Tucson Gas, Electric Light and Power Company, electrical engineering work, businesses and other locations throughout Tucson and the rest of Arizona and trips to California, Montana and Mexico.
5.4 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/ E-Mail: LBRY-askspcoll@email.arizona.edu
Restrictions
The following materials are restricted from access:
Box 7 Folder 3; Box 8 Folder 1 and Folder 17; Box 9 Folder 2; Box 10 Folder 9; Box 15
Please contact the archivist for assistance.
Biographical Note
Arthur Eugene "Gene" Magee, born in 1907, moved from Oklahoma to Tucson with his family in 1924. Magee graduated from Tucson High School in 1925 and received his B.S. in electrical engineering from the University of Arizona in 1930. He began working full time at Tucson Gas, Electric Light and Power Company (now TEP) and photographing his electrical work, a practice that continued throughout his career. Magee became the manager at Tucson Rapid Transit Company (now Sun Tran) for eight years in the late 1930s and co-founded Western Ways Photographic Services with photographer and filmmaker Charles Herbert in 1946. In 1948, Magee started his own company Magee Engineering in 1948 and left Western Ways to focus on his new business. Magee spent the next 48 years operating his firm working on over 100 schools, over 30 buildings on the University of Arizona campus, Tucson International Airport, City Hall and a variety of other buildings across Tucson. In addition to his engineering career, Magee became a licensed pilot in the 1930s and began taking aerial photos of Tucson, effectively documenting the city's post-WWII population growth over several decades. Throughout his life, Magee also traveled and photographed several cities across Arizona, McLeod, Montana, some popular destinations in California and across northern Mexico, including many missions founded by Father Kino. In 1995, Magee contributed some of his aerial images to Above Tucson Now and Then by James Glinski, a book comparing aerial views taken by Magee in the 1940s to views taken by Glinski in 1995.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 4 series and 13 subseries:
Series I: Tucson, 1902, circa 1920-1996
Sub-Series 1: Aerials, circa 1930-1996
Sub-Series 2: Aviation, circa 1940-1996
Sub-Series 3: Locations, 1902, circa 1930-1996
Sub-Series 4: Schools, circa 1960-1990
Sub-Series 5: Tucson Gas, Electric Light and Power Company, 1902-1950
Sub-Series 6: Miscellaneous, 1939-1963
Sub-Series 7: Oversize Tucson, circa 1930-1996
Series II: Arizona, circa 1930-1990
Sub-Series 1: Arizona Cities, circa 1930-1990
Sub-Series 2: Miscellaneous, undated
Sub-Series 3: Oversize Arizona, 1939-1950, 1975, 1984
Series III: United States and Mexico, 1936-1960
Sub-Series 1: United States, 1940-1960
Sub-Series 2: Mexico, 1936-1937
Sub-Series 3: Oversize U.S. and Mexico, 1936-1937, 1940
Series IV: Printed Materials, 1952, 1972, 1978, 1996
Scope and Content Note
This collection has four series and contains photographic materials consisting of black and white and color negatives of varying formats from 35mm, medium and large format film and color slides, black and white and color prints of varying sizes, contact sheets, postcards, a small number of papers created or kept by Magee and a small selection of photographs from other Western Ways photographers, Manley Commercial Photography and the Buehman Collection. Many negatives have little to no background information recorded. Materials in this collection date from 1902-1996, the majority between 1930-1970, and document both aerial and ground views of Tucson, several cities across Arizona and trips to California, Montana and Mexico.
The first series pertains to Tucson from 1902-1996 and is divided into seven sub-series organized at folder level and consists of aerials of Tucson spanning several decades, airports and air shows in and around Tucson, a variety of buildings, ranches and other locations including a large number of schools Magee completed electrical work at, views of the Tucson Gas, Electric Light and Power Company plant and miscellaneous events and sights around Tucson like the Tucson Rodeo and its annual parade. The final sub-series contains oversize reproductions of materials found in the first six sub-series.
The second series pertains to several cities across Arizona from 1930-1970 and is divided into three sub-series organized at folder level. Magee did not record specific information such as dates for a bulk of these materials. The first series is organized by city and the subjects found in each city vary greatly from aerials, businesses, dams, ghost towns, hotels, mills, mining, Native Americans, ranches, scenery and schools. The second series consists of images of national and state parks and unidentified aerials, cacti, ranches and scenery and the third series contains oversize reproductions of works from the first two sub-series.
The third series pertains to travel outside of Arizona from 1940-1960 and is divided into three sub-series organized at folder level. The first sub-series includes popular destinations in California and scenes from McLeod, Montana. The second sub-series includes photographs from a trip Gene and his wife Pauline Magee took to Mexico in 1936 or 1937 where they visited many of Father Kino's missions, multiple cities, the country side, beaches and Rancho Alamo. The third sub-series contains oversize reproductions of materials found in the first two sub-series.
The fourth series contains a small selection of printed materials including personal letters sent to Magee, a volume of "Creative Ideas in Glass" containing a feature on an addition to the El Con Shopping Mall where Magee completed work as an electrical engineer, a newsletter from the West University Neighborhood Association and a "special list stock cards."
A.E. Magee Collection (PC 177). Arizona Historical Society, Tucson, Archives Department.
Above Tucson: then & now by James Glinski; with Gene Magee's vintage photographs and a foreword by Roy P. Drachman.
Buehman Family Collection (MS 1240). Arizona Historical Society, Tucson, Archives Department.
The Western Ways Feature Files Collection (MS 1056). Arizona Historical Society, Tucson, Archives Department.
Access Terms
Magee, A. E. (Gene).
Magee Engineering.
Western Ways Photographic Services.
Aerial Photography -- Arizona.
Documentary photography--United States--History--20th century.
Electrical Engineering.
Photography -- Arizona -- Tucson.
Arizona -- Pictorial works.
California -- Pictorial works.
Mexico -- Pictorial works.
Montana -- Pictorial works.
Tucson (Ariz.) -- Pictorial works.
Container List
- Tucson, 1902, circa 1920-1996; Series I
  This series has seven subseries. It contains mostly black and white and some color 35 mm, medium and large format negatives and prints of varying sizes, printed materials, postcards and some color slides of locations within the city of Tucson and the surrounding area.
  - Aerials, circa 1930-1996; Subseries 1
    This series is arranged alphabetically and described at folder level and contains black and white aerial negatives and prints of various parts of Tucson spanning several decades taken during Magee's frequent flights over the city. Prints in the identified folder note street names and are often dated by Magee.
    - Downtown -- negatives and photos, circa 1970-1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Identified -- negatives and photos, circa 1930-1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Tucson Residences -- negatives, 1941, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Unidentified -- negatives, circa 1930-1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Unidentified -- photos, circa 1930-1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Aviation, circa 1940-1996; Subseries 2
    This series is described at folder level and is arranged alphabetically. It contains mostly black and white and some color negatives and prints including many aerial images from various early airports that have been demolished, repurposed or remodeled, the first incarnation of the Tucson International Airport where Magee worked as the engineer of record, air shows and a space shuttle launch.
    - Avra Valley Air Show -- negatives and photos, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Davis Monthan Air Force Base -- photo, circa 1940-1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Gilpin Airport -- negatives, circa 1940-1950 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Gilpin Airport -- photos, circa 1940-1950 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Lockheed Hanger -- negatives and prints, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Space Shuttle Launch -- negatives, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Tucson Airport -- Hodgin Family, Terminal -- negatives, circa 1940-1950 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Tucson Airport -- Terminal -- negatives, circa 1940-1950 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Grand Central -- photos, circa 1950-1955 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Tucson Airport -- printed materials, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Tucson Air Show -- negatives, circa 1970-1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Locations, 1902, circa 1930-1996; Subseries 3
    This series is described at folder level and is arranged alphabetically. It contains mostly black and white and some color negatives and prints including some aerial images, printed materials and some color slides of a variety of businesses, sport fields, popular destinations like San Xavier Mission and Saguaro National Park and other buildings in Tucson, many of which Magee did electrical work for.
    - Arizona Historical Society -- Manley Commercial Photography -- prints, circa 1960-1970 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Arizona Inn -- print, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Arizona Sonora Desert Museum -- Western Ways -- negatives and prints, 1938, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Arizona Trust Company -- prints, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Baseball field (railroad tracks and Speedway) -- prints, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Colossal Cave -- negative and print, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Congress St. Bridge Statues -- negatives, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - DeGrazia Gallery in the Sun -- slides, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Downtown: East side of Park at railroad tracks -- prints, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Downtown: assorted buildings -- negatives and prints, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Elks Club / Snob Hollow -- prints, circa 1970-1980 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Fort Lowell Site -- print, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - General Electric -- Gates Learjet Lighting -- prints, printed materials, circa 1970-1980, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Hi Corbett Field -- negatives and prints, 1992-1993, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Infilco, South Campbell Ave. -- prints, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Lodge in the Desert -- negatives, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Miracle Mile -- prints, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Old Tucson -- negatives and slides, 1958, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Plaza International -- print, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Pima County Court House, Western Ways / Peter Balestrero -- prints, circa 1950-1960 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Pond's Mansion -- prints, 1946, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Red & Blue Drive-In -- Arthur Brown -- negative, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Ranches: Desert Haven Trailer Court, Diamond W Ranch, Double A Ranch, Double U Ranch, Flying V Ranch, Rancho del Rio -- negatives, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Saguaro National Park -- negatives, prints and color slides, 1958, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - San Xavier Mission -- negatives, prints and color slides, circa 1940-1950, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - San Xavier Mission: Tucson Boys' Choir -- negatives, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Sandpit at Speedway and Pantano -- print, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Softball Field: S. 3rd St. and 22nd St. -- prints, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Southern Arizona Bank and Trust Co. -- negatives and prints, 1971, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - St. Philips in the Hills Church -- negative and photo, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Tucson Carnegie Library / Tucson Children's Museum -- print, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Tucson City Hall -- print, circa 1960-1970 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Tucson Community Center -- negatives, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Tucson Fire Station Corner Park fire simulator -- negatives, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Tucson House Hotel -- negative and prints, circa 1960-1970 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Tucson Rapid Transit Co. -- negatives, 1937-1944 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Tucson Rock and Sand Co. -- negatives, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Union Bank -- negative and prints, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - VA Hospital -- prints, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - YMCA, W. Congress -- prints, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - YMCA, 6th St. and 35th Ave. -- Manley Commercial Photography / Peter Balestrero -- prints, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Schools, circa 1960-1990; Subseries 4
    This series is described at folder level and is arranged alphabetically. It contains mostly black and white and some color negatives and prints and a postcard including aerial and interior images depicting schools throughout Tucson, including the University of Arizona.
    - Canyon del Oro High School Football Field -- negatives and prints, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Catalina High School Gym -- prints, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Gale Elementary -- prints, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - John B. Wright School -- prints, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Marana High School -- negatives and prints, 1976, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Menlo Park School -- negatives, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Pima Community College aerials -- prints, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Pima Community College Performing Arts Center (photographed by Robert Davis), Communications Center and Art Gallery -- negatives and prints, 1991, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Pima Community College switchboard / transformer -- negatives and prints, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Sahuaro High School -- prints, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Tucson High School -- negatives and postcard, 1989, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - University of Arizona aerials -- negatives and prints, 1989, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - University of Arizona Chemistry Building -- negatives and prints, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - University of Arizona Fine Arts Building -- negatives and prints, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - University of Arizona Main Library -- negatives and prints, 1978, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - University of Arizona McKale Memorial Center -- negatives and prints, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - University of Arizona School of Medicine exterior and aerials -- negatives and prints, 1971, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - University of Arizona School of Medicine interior -- negatives and prints, 1969, 1971, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - University of Arizona Miscellaneous Buildings -- negatives and prints, 1968, 1975, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - University of Arizona Optical Sciences Building -- negatives and prints, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - University of Arizona Science and Engineering Library -- negatives and prints, 1973, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Tucson Gas, Electric Light and Power Co., circa 1902-1950; Subseries 5
    This series is described at folder level and arranged alphabetically and contains not only some of the earliest black and white negatives and prints made by Magee, but a selection of prints from the Buehman collection taken in 1902 of the interior and exterior of the old Tucson Gas, Electric Light and Power Co. power plant. Also pictured are several employees, aerial views of the plant and abstract images of industrial details in addition to small amount of printed materials.
    - Buehman photos, old power plant -- prints, 1902 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Fort Huachuca Pole Line -- prints, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Power plant aerials -- prints, 1950, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Power plant exterior -- prints, circa 1920-1930, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Power plant interior -- prints, circa 1920-1930, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Printed materials, 1902, 1925 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Turbine and first power plant -- negatives, 1937, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1939-1963; Subseries 6
    This series is described at folder level and arranged alphabetically and contains black and white negatives and prints. It contains miscellaneous subject matter within the city of Tucson like the Tucson Rodeo and parade and baby owls.
    - Baby Owls -- negatives, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Circus -- negatives, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Father Kino plaque at City Hall -- negatives, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Tucson area mountain ranges -- negatives and print, 1945-1949 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Tucson Mid-Winter Rodeo -- negatives, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Tucson Rodeo Parade and Rodeo -- negatives and color slides, circa 1939-1950, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Tucson Rodeo Parade and Rodeo -- negatives and prints, 1946-1947 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Unidentified instrument -- print, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Vasquez, ornamental iron worker -- negatives and prints, undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Oversize Tucson, circa 1930-1996; Subseries 7
    This series is described at box level and has no organization. It contains mostly black and white and some color oversize reproductions of images from the first set of series within the collection.
    - Contents include Arizona Stadium, Avra Valley Air Show, country scenery east of Rincons, Canyon del Oro High School football field lighting, aerials of Downtown Tucson (some including the rodeo parade) and views of buildings from the ground, aerials of Hi-Corbett Field, McKale Center, Saguaro National Park, aerial of San Xavier Mission, Southern Arizona Bank and Trust Co., St. Phillips in the Hills Episcopal Church, Tucson Gas, Electric Light and Power Co., Tucson House, aerials of University of Arizona Medical School and other aerial views of campus., circa 1930-1996 (Box 6A)
- Arizona, circa 1930-1984; Series 2
  This series has three sub-series and contains black and white and some color negatives and prints of varying sizes, color slides and postcards.
  - Arizona cities, circa 1930-1990; Subseries 1
    This series is described at folder level and is organized alphabetically by location. It contains color slides, mostly black and white and some color 35 mm, medium and large format negatives and prints of varying sizes and postcards of various subjects from businesses, mining and other industries, scenery, dams, ranches, schools, Native American reservations and ghost towns within cities and counties across Arizona. Creation dates of the materials were seldom noted by Magee.
    - Ajo: Phelps Dodge Copper Mill, New Cornelia open pit mine -- negatives, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Amado: Amado Golf Course, Kinsley Ranch, Kinsley Ranch Rodeo, Sopori Ranch -- negatives, 1946, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Apache Reservation: Apache family -- negative (restricted), undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Arivaca: scenery -- negatives, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Benson: Cattle ranch, Southern Pacific Railroad aerials -- negatives, 1948, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Bisbee: Warren area aerials -- negatives and prints, 1949, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Bowie: Desert Rose Gift Shop -- negatives, prints, postcard, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Douglas: Wonderland of Rocks -- negative, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Elgin: aerials, Collie Ranch, Diamond C Ranch at Canelo, scenics -- negatives, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Flagstaff: Northern Arizona University library and teaching building -- negatives, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Globe: Coolidge Dam, Highway 60 (Salt River area), Gila County Hospital, Griffin Ranch -- negatives and prints, 1946-1947, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Greer: Turner's Hilltop Lodge -- negatives and prints, 1942 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Havasupai: residents and scenics, Western Ways -- prints (restricted), undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Kitt Peak Observatory -- negatives and slides, 1963, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Mammoth: Collins Stone, Crystal Lake, Pony Express Rider Shorty Neal, smelters, Sombrero Butte -- negatives, 1946, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Marana Way: deer, scenics -- negatives, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Maricopa County: Mormon Flat Dam -- negatives, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - McNary: General Store, Southwest Mills Inc., theater -- negatives and prints, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Mohave County: Hoover Dam -- negatives, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Nogales: Mexican Air Force, Rancho Guevavi aerials -- negatives, 1939-1940, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Oracle: Church, cattle corral, Mountain View Hotel, Oracle Inn, Rancho Robles, schools, Western Antiques -- negatives, 1937, 1944-1946, undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Oracle Junction: Am. Smelting and Roofing Co. -- negatives and prints, 1949 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Patagonia: aerials, Circle Z Guest Ranch, Jeffcott Ranch, Wilshaw Ranch -- negatives, undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Phoenix: Chris Town Center -- prints, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Sahuarita: aerial of mill, Western Ways / M. T. Thomas -- print, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Santa Cruz County, Nogales Highway: Howell Manning Ranch, Hugh Merryweather ranch house, Kenyon Ranch, Rancho Chiquito -- negatives, undated (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Sedona: Chapel of the Holy Cross, wagon wheel -- negatives, 1938 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Sells: Aerial, ball field, circus -- negatives and color slides, 1971, undated (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Sells: Indian cowboys -- negatives (restricted), undated (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Show Low: Becker Butte, Charlson Sawmill, fish hatchery, Kinishba Curio, Nava-Pache Hospital, Ponderosa Park, Show Low scenics, Show Low Hospital -- negatives and prints, 1946, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Sierra Vista: Apaches, Western Ways -- negatives, prints, postcards (restricted), 1987, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Sierra Vista: Ft. Huachuca and housing, Western Ways -- negatives and prints, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Silver Bell: aerials -- negatives, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Sonoita: Haciendo Los Euciuos aerial, Sonoita Rodeo -- negatives, 1938-1939, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Superior Highway: AZ State Route 177, Pinal County aerials -- negatives, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Thatcher: Eastern Arizona Junior College -- negatives and prints, 1955 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Three Points: aerial -- negatives, undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Tiger -- negatives, undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Tombstone: Ed Schieffelin, scenics, World's Largest Rose Tree -- negatives and prints, undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Tubac: Otero Ranch, Rancho Santa Cruz -- negatives and prints, undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Tumacacori: Tumacacori Mission, Western Ways -- negatives, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - White Hills: scenics -- negatives and prints, 1935-1936, 1940 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Willcox: Three Links Ranch -- prints, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Yuma: Arizona Western College, sand dunes -- negatives and prints, circa 1940-1960 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous, undated; Subseries 2